Welcome to the presentation of DataLad Catalog:
a free and open source command line tool, with a Python API,
that lets you create user-friendly, browser-based data catalogs from structured metadata.
The importance and benefits of making research data Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable are clear.
But of equal importance are our legal and ethical obligations to protect the personal data privacy of research participants.
So we are struck with this apparent contradiction: how can we share our data openly…yet keep it secure and protected?
Should we err on the side of FAIRness, or of data privacy? And do we even have to choose?
Ideally, no. And in practice, also no,
because we have a powerful opportunity in the form of linked, structured, and machine-readable metadata.
Metadata provides not only high-level information about our research data, such as study and data acquisition parameters,
but also the descriptive aspects of each file in the dataset, such as file paths, sizes, and formats.
With this metadata, we can create an abstract representation of the full dataset that is separate from the actual data content.
This means that the content can be stored securely, while we openly share the metadata to make our work more FAIR.
As an added benefit, structured and machine-readable metadata that conforms to industry standards
improves the interoperability and allows the use of automated pipelines and tools.
These ideals are achievable in practice, with a toolset that includes the distributed data management system DataLad,
and its extensions for metadata handling and catalog generation.
DataLad can be used for decentralised management of data as lightweight, portable and extensible representations.
Datalad-metalad can extract structured high- and low-level metadata and associate it with these datasets or with individual files.
And at the end of the workflow, Datalad-catalog can turn the structured metadata into a user-friendly data browser!
So how does the catalog generation process work?
Metadata extracted from various sources, even custom sources,
can be aggregated and added to a catalog.
Incoming metadata will first be validated
against a catalog-specific schema,
before the catalog is generated or individual entries are added.
Once the process is finished,
the output is a set of structured metadata files,
as well as a Vue.js-based browser interface
that understands how to render this metadata.
What is left for the user
is to host this content on their platform of choice
and serve it for the world to see.
Datalad catalog brings the powerful functionality of decentralised metadata handling and data publishing into the hands of users,
preventing dependence on centralised infrastructure and keeping private data secure while adhering to FAIR principles.
Please explore the demo catalog, walk through the interactive tutorial
or visit the codebase to start using or contributing to datalad catalog.